<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ exalted, and alone worthy to open the seals of the book. And the scriptures owned in their place. A true testimony of him, as is manifest, in answer to a book, intituled, The Quakers apostacy, from the perfect rule of scriptures. Given forth by John Timson, of Great Bowden in Leicestershire. And the deceits and blasphemies he charges upon the Quakers, is turned upon his own head, and he found guilty of what he reproaches them with, in what is written for the simples sake, and truth to clear from false accusations and lyes cast upon it. And the ten queries he saith he vindicateth, and would print but foure of them, they are all published, with the answers that he charges to be confused, dark and deceitfull, that the answers may witnesse for themselves against what is charged upon them. He that hath an understanding in the light, read and judge. / William Dewsberry.</title>
            <author>Dewsbury, William, 1621-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E891_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 134:E891[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ exalted, and alone worthy to open the seals of the book. And the scriptures owned in their place. A true testimony of him, as is manifest, in answer to a book, intituled, The Quakers apostacy, from the perfect rule of scriptures. Given forth by John Timson, of Great Bowden in Leicestershire. And the deceits and blasphemies he charges upon the Quakers, is turned upon his own head, and he found guilty of what he reproaches them with, in what is written for the simples sake, and truth to clear from false accusations and lyes cast upon it. And the ten queries he saith he vindicateth, and would print but foure of them, they are all published, with the answers that he charges to be confused, dark and deceitfull, that the answers may witnesse for themselves against what is charged upon them. He that hath an understanding in the light, read and judge. / William Dewsberry.</title>
                  <author>Dewsbury, William, 1621-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A response to: Timson, John.  The Quakers apostacie.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 7th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Timson, John. --  Quakers apostacie --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117904:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRIST
EXALTED,
<hi>AND</hi>
Alone worthy to open the Seals of the Book. And the Scriptures owned in their place. <hi>A</hi>
True TESTIMONY of him, as
is manifeſt, in Anſwer to a Book, Intituled,
<hi>The Quakers Apoſtacy, from the perfect Rule
of Scriptures.</hi> Given forth by <hi>John Timſon,</hi> of
Great <hi>Bowden</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire.</hi> And the Deceits and Blaſphemies he charges
upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> is turned upon his own head, and
he found guilty of what he reproaches them with, in what
is written for the ſimples ſake, and truth to clear
from falſe accuſations and lyes caſt upon it. And the Ten <hi>Queries</hi> he ſaith he vindicateth,
and would Print but foure of them, they are
all publiſhed, with the Anſwers that he charges to be
confuſed, dark and deceitfull, that the Anſwers
may witneſſe for themſelves againſt what
is charged upon them. He that hath an underſtanding in the light, read and judge.</p>
            <p>WILLIAM DEWSBERRY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternall life, and
they are they which teſtifie of me. And ye will not come to me,
that ye might have life.</p>
               <bibl>John 5. 39, 40.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Jeſus ſaith unto him, I am the way, and the truth, and the life, no
man cometh unto the father, but by me,</p>
               <bibl>John 14. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117904:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117904:2"/>
            <head>Chriſt Exalted,
AND
Alone worthy to open the Seals of the Book,
And the Scriptures owned in their place, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>John Timſon.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Book thou hath Printed, is ſeen with the light that
returned an Anſwer to thy firſt <hi>Queries;</hi> and for the
truths ſake, and it to clear, from the lies, ſlanders, and
aſperſions caſt upon it, in the light here is writ, to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
againſt the falſhood and untruth, which thou haſt charged us
withall, that anſwers thy <hi>Queries,</hi> which to that of God in all
conſciences, who it minds, will give them to diſcern, that what
thou haſt charged againſt the people, who in ſcorn are called
<hi>Quakers,</hi> is falſe, and on thee is returned, as the lines following
make manifeſt, wherein is writ what thou haſt charged them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
and to clear the truth, an anſwer thereunto is returned.</p>
            <p>In thy Preface as thou calls it, which thou preſents to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
thou haſt not much of it expreſt, before thou begins falſly to
accuſe us, charging us with drawing people aſide, and intangling
them with dark Diabolicall ſnares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thou ſaith, The anſwers thou received to thy ten <hi>Queries,</hi>
were ſo obſcure, deceitfull, and confuſed, that it conſtrained thee
to Reply. To which thou ſaith, an Anſwer thou haſt received, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
and hath now undertaken to give the ſenſe of what thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands
of what is writ to thee, and hath given it forth publickly to
the world, that we have accuſed thee of ſlanders, in things that are
too groſſe in plainneſſe of ſpeech, to publiſh to the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117904:3"/>
               <hi>Reply:</hi> Darke diabolical ſnares we deny, the word of the Lord
God we witneſſe which was in the beginning, which word is life
and the life is the light of men. <hi>John.</hi> 1. 1. 4. which word we
preach to turn the mindes of people from darkneſſe to light;
from the power of Satan to the liveing God, <hi>Acts.</hi> 26. 18. in the
light of his liveing word, which diſcovers the thoughts and intents
of the heart: <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. to waite in his light, on him for power,
to lead out of all the waies of darkneſſe, into union with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of life, in Chriſt the light, who in him walke, there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of ſtumbling; <hi>Jo.</hi> 2. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but who deny to be guided by his
ſpirit is none of his; <hi>Ro. 8 ver.</hi> 9. but in darkneſſe walke and
ſtumble at noon day, and it is truth we declare, as it is recorded
in the Scripture of truth, he that can receive it, let him, and for
thy charging the anſwer to be obſcure, deceitfull, and confuſed,
ſeeing the deceit in thee, hath publiſhed that they are deceitfull,
and could not publiſh them to make manifeſt what the deceit is
and ſome of them which thou haſt publiſhed thou hath both ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
and diminiſhed, for the truths ſake, the queries with their
anſwers is publiſhed, that the anſwer may witneſſe for it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the falſhood thou haſt charged on it, he that hath an eye to
ſee let him ſee;</p>
            <p>And for thy giveing thy ſence of what thou underſtands of our
writeing and ſaith we accuſe thee of ſlandering <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> Thy ſence thou gives of our words with thy dark un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
we deny, and ſlandering we deny, it is thy owne
practiſe, proved to thy face, by thy owne words, as followeth.
Second falſe accuſation.</p>
            <p>2. Thou ſayes, that we judge our novices, and all others beſides
our ſelves u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peable to receive ſome of our principles, as yet, and
therefore we ſtudy to darken the ſence, by ſubtill glozing, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating
expreſſions, and ſhuffles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi> Thy falſe accuſation we deny, we doe not judge Novices
beſides our ſelves uncapeable to receive our principles, we know
Chriſt the true light hath lighted every one that comes into the
world, and the Goſpel we preach, is to turn the mindes of people,
from darkneſſe to light, and who it minds it will give them an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
the principle of pure religion to know, Chriſt the
light in whom we ſtand cleare of thy ſlanders, in his light we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117904:3"/>
plainly ſpeake as moved of him, and doe not ſtudy to darken the
ſence of our wordes, as thou doſt falſely accuſe us, the Lord is
Judge between thee and us.</p>
            <p>3. The third accuſation charging us with damnable hereſies,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and further thou ſayeſt, what thou haſt charged us withall
is upon ſuch rationall grounds, that thou art ſure we are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
in the ſecret of our hearts and Conſciences that thou lyes
not; In the preſence of God I charge thee to be a lyar, in the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
and lyes before written, what followeth will make thee
more manifeſt; thou ſayeſt we frequently judge men by the light
which gave forth the Scripture, even while we are oppoſing the
authority of Scriptures, as they are the only rule of knowing
God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy charge is falſe, in ſaying we oppoſe the authority of
Scriptures which Chriſt the light who gave forth the Scripture,
who ſpake as one haveing authority and not as the Scribes, <hi>Mat.</hi>
7. 29. and the Scripture is a true teſtimony of him who is the
way to the father, <hi>none knowes the father but the ſon and he to whom
the ſon reveales him, Mat.</hi> 11. 27. ſo thou in the light art ſeene
to be guilty of what thou chargeſt us withall, in denying Chriſt
the light, within, to be the authority of Scriptures, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
rule of faith and obedience, therefore let fleſh be ſilent, and
the lying mouth be ſtopped, for Chriſt we own, which was before
the Scriptures, and is the authority of them, for when he ſpoke
them forth he ſpoke as one haveing authority and according as
Chriſt ſpeaketh of the Scriptures, we them own in their place;
a true teſtimony of him, <hi>Jo. 5. 39, 40. who is the way the truth and
the life, and no man cometh to the father but by him. Jo.</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>So none comes to the knowledge of the father by reading the
Scriptures though they think to finde life there, they ſhall not,
if they come not to Chriſt, of whom they teſtifie, and in whom
the life is, who ſaith <hi>ſearch the Scriptures for in them ye think to
have eternall life,</hi> and they are they which teſtifie of me, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves
all who will not come to him that they may have life. So
what thou charges us withall, thou art the man that denys the
authority of Scriptures, and found guilty of ſlandering the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
of light, as what is written makes manifeſt and what as
followeth will make thee more manifeſt to all that have eyes to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117904:4"/>
ſee the many falſhhoods and lyes thou haſt begun the booke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
in that thou calls the preface to the reader, ſo out of thy
owne mouth thou art condemned.</p>
            <p>4. The fourth falſe accuſation, thou ſayſt we are ſo drunk with
deluſion and impudency, that we will rather charge the Scripture
with deceit then queſtion our owne deceitfull hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> In the preſence of God we witneſſe againſt thee, we
owne the Scripture to be the Scripture of truth and do not charge
the Scripture with deceit, but with the light of Chriſt that gave
forth the Scriptures, and diſcovereth the deceit of the heart, with
which light we judge the deceit of the heart, and witneſſe againſt
thee in the light, which makes known to us the Scripture in the
truth as it is in Jeſus Chriſt the light God is our witneſſe.</p>
            <p>5. The fifth falſe accuſation, thou ſayſt we rite and ſpeak
the L<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nguage of Scripture as if we were for it, and is not, which is
rancke hypocriſy and done of purpoſe to deceive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> We in the light ſpeak as moved of the Lord 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.
21. whoſe Language is according to Scripture, and doing any
thing in hypocriſy we deny, as to deceive any the Lord is our
witneſſe, who will rebuke the lying ſpirit, and ſtop thy lying
mouth.</p>
            <p>6. The ſixth falſe accuſation, thou ſayſt we boaſt, that we are
as perfect as Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy charge is falſe, boaſting we deny, or any perfection
that is of ſelf, our righteouſneſſe without Chriſt is as a filthy ragg;
and a menſtruous cloth, Chriſt our righteouſneſſe, who is the
true light, <hi>that lighteth every one that comes into the world, Jo.</hi> 1. 9.
we witneſſe him the ſame Chriſt, as was in that body that ſuffered
at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and every one of the Children of light in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of growth in him, the ſame minde is in them, that was in
Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 5. who is the brightneſſe of the fathers
glory, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
            <p>7. The ſeventh falſe accuſation, thou ſayſt we ſay, that he that
truſts in Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for Salvation, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This charge is falſe as the other, in the preſence of God
we witneſſe againſt thee, no other Chriſt we bear teſtimony of to
be the ſalvation of loſt man and woman, but that Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117904:4"/>
to Scripture teſtimony, who was born of the virgin and bore
a good confeſſion before <hi>Pilate,</hi> and ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and
roſe again the third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at
the right hand of God, and this Chriſt we witneſſe the true light,
<hi>who lighteth every one that comes into the world,</hi> and ſaith I ſtand
at the door and knock, who opens, <hi>I will come into him and ſup
with him, and he with me, Rev.</hi> 3. 20. and we witneſſe him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:
<hi>and as many as receives him, to them he gives power, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
the Sons of God,</hi> and this is the condemnation of all, becauſe
they beleeve not in him. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
            <p>8. The eight falſe accuſation, thou ſayſt we reproach Chriſts
inſtitutions and holy ordinances, with the odium of mens tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
outward obſervations inconſiſtent with Gods Kingdome,
and compares them to <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> great Idol, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy Charge is falſe, Chriſts inſtitutions, and holy
ordinances, we owne in the diſpenſation of time they were to be
continued, and what is now in this diſpenſation of time known
in the adminiſtration of his ſpirit, we owne, but who upholds any
Idolatry, in obſerving any thing by tradition, and not guided by
the Spirit of Chriſt, and ſo walke contrary to the perfect Law of
God in the Conſcience; and though their words be never ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
in outward appearance, in crying the Ordinances of Chriſt,
while they deny to be guided by Chriſt, they are no Ordinances
of Chriſt, but an Image, ſet up in the proud exalted nature, which
<hi>Nebuchad nezzar</hi> ſet up his Image in which with the power of
God ſhall be throwne downe and thou with the reſt of the Idol
worſhipers ſhall be broken to peices and lyes ſhall not ſave
thee, for the Lord will exalt his name and his Children that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
his holy ordinances ſhall reigne in his his ſpirituall power,
that preſerves them therein to obſerve the moveings of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
which doth lead to worſhip the father, in ſpirit and truth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to teſtimony of Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 23, 24.</p>
            <p>And when thou <hi>John Timſon</hi> haſt preſented thy falſe accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and lyes to the Reader, in the preface of thy Booke, that
they might receive the falſehoods, and lyes that are written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
and theſe lyes and ſlanders, which are here laid before thee,
and witneſſed againſt, in the anſwer there to returned will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienly
prove to thy face, and be manifeſt to that of God in every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117904:5"/>
ones Conſcience, that thou haſt ſpoken unadviſedly with thy lips,
when thou ſayſt thou lies not, and all theſe lies found in thy mouth,
given forth publiquely for all to read and thou declares to the
Reader that the Lord knows, what diligence and tenderneſſe of
bowels, thou haſt had to prepare it for them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Bluſh for ſhame O vain man to appeale to the Lords
knowledge of thy d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gence and tenderneſſe of bowels, to prepare
ſo many lyes and falſhoods for people to read thou ſhalt certainly
know that the Lord takes notice of thee, and he wil lay thee open,
and make thee manifeſt, and lyes ſhall not cover thee, nor be thy
refuge; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 17. when our God will clear his truth, and thy
tongue, and all others, that riſe up againſt him, ſhall fall in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
the day ſhall declare it.</p>
            <p>Further thou goes on ſaying, as for thoſe perſons that have
anſwered me who have charged me with bringing forth many
lyes and ſlanders, and have made a noiſe thereof, as if I were
ſome carnall lying wretch, that matters not what I write.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> To that of God in every ones conſcience I appeale, that
lyes proceed from a Carnall wretched heart, and the Lord is
making thee manifeſt, who would make lyes thy refuge;
which with the light thou art ſeen, and thy lyes turned upon thee,
that in the light thou mayſt be read what thou art, and in the
light our Books are known, and no ſuch thing is in our Books as
thou falſely charges us with, and would make people believe is
written therein, in giving the ſence of our words in thy dark mind,
and for the Simples ſake, an anſwer is returned, to clear the truth
of God in what he hath given out by his ſpirit, both in word and
writing, and whether thou wilt receive it yea, or nay, thou ſhalt
know and all others, that Chriſt is the authority of the Scripture,
and when he ſpoke them forth, he ſpake as one having authority
and not as a Scribe, &amp; who in his light walk, cannot be perſwaded
to turn from him, by any lyes and reproaches thou can caſt upon
them, who ſayſt we are wholly turned from the truth, which
againſt thee witneſſe it is not ſo, let God be judge, and in his
day make manifeſt what we are in whoſe will we reſt, as moved
of him to witneſſe againſt the falſhoods, thou haſt further char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
upon us in what followeth.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt not done juſtly nor honeſtly in that thou haſt not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117904:5"/>
Printed the queſtions as given forth by thee, and anſwers as retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by us, and in an anſwer to what is of thee required, to prove
the charge thou charges us withall, in thy reply to the anſwer to
the firſt Queſtion, and the falſe accuſations, lyes and ſlanders
is not proved in all thou haſt writ.</p>
            <p>The one baptiſme we owne <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5. and the watch in the
Church we owne, in the ſpirit of life, which in order doth keepe,
in obedience to the pure God, who is the God of order, and not of
confuſion, but keeps his Children in himſelf purely to live, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to what is pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt.</p>
            <p>Further thou goes on and queries, what proofe would we have,
is it not our owne prophane language, both in papers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
it is no ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to hear moſt of their way, diſpute againſt
water Baptiſm, the Lords Supper, a ſettled fixed Miniſtry over
particular Churches, and queries, further, what Quakers admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
water baptiſme, the Lords Supper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſtantly watches
over a particular flock, or elſe for ſhame thou ſayſt we muſt own
the charge, and confeſſe our ſin, in telling the world theſe are thy
lying ſlanders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Prophane Language we deny, and ſhadowes and figures
we witneſſe done away, the ſubſtance being come, water baptiſm
was in its time a figure of the ſubſtance, as <hi>John</hi> witneſſes, to whom
that diſpenſation was committed, <hi>Mat. 3. 11. I indeed baptize
with water unto Repentance, but he that comes after me is mightier
then I, whoſe ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es I am not worthy to bear, he ſhall baptize you
with the Holy ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with fire.</hi> And <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme we deny to
be in force, he did decreaſe and Chriſt muſt increaſe whoſe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
we own, according as is recorded in the Scripture of truth,
and ſince he aſcended, there is no Scripture doth witneſſe his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
any to baptize with water, <hi>Paul</hi> who was ſent
after he aſcended, what he did in the liberty given him,
his liberty he knew, when he circumſciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> and baptized
<hi>Criſpus,</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and the houſehold of <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phanus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> beſides I
know not th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I baptized any other ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> for Chriſt ſent me
not to baptize but to preach the Goſpel, not with wiſedome of
words, leaſt the croſſe of Chriſt ſhould be of none effect,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 16, 17. And <hi>John</hi> who bare record, of the word of
the word of God, and teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 6.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117904:6"/>
ſaith I ſaw an Angel in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting
Goſpel to preach to them that dwell in the earth, and to every
Nation, and Kindred, tongue and People, <hi>John</hi> did not ſay, he
did fly through the midſt of heaven preaching the everlaſting
Goſpel, and baptizing with water, we know <hi>John</hi> faithfull in his
teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, who is now revealed, and the Angell
is come, and the Goſpel preached and the ſhadowes done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>And Bread and Wine were the Supper of the Lord, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation
of time, a figure of his death, which were fulfilled, when
he had ſuffered and roſe again, and now he is known to ſtand at
the door and knock, if any man heare my voice, and open the
door, <hi>I will come in and Sup with him, and he with me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 20. And we being many are one bread, and one body,
<hi>&amp;c. 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 17. and knows the wine renewed in our fathers
Kingdome, Chriſt the ſubſtance we now witneſſe, ſhadows and
figures done away, he that can receive it let him.</p>
            <p>And the Churches ſet up by the will of man, we deny, and the
fixed miniſtry ſet up over them by the will of man, that watch
for the fleece, beare rule by their means, and ſeeks their gain from
their quarter, theſe we deny; <hi>Jer. 5. 31. Iſa.</hi> 56. 11.</p>
            <p>And thoſe in ſcorn called Quakers, doth watch over the flock of
God, every one as the Lord them calls, and not for filthy lucre, as
the Prieſts that bear rule by their means do, neither by conſtraint,
but of a ready minde 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2. in obedience to the ſpirit of the
Lord, as he them moves, and thy ſlanders thou haſt not yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
our conſcience doth witneſſe it, that what thou haſt accuſed
us with is a lye, and not the truth.</p>
            <p>And thou further ſayes that <hi>Will. Deuſberry</hi> in a lying paper,
as thou calls it, which is entituled <hi>A true prophecy of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
day of the Lord already riſen in the North of England, &amp;c.</hi> in
which paper he makes it his worke, to ſlander the Ordinances of
Goſpel worſhip, under the notion of outward obſervations,
which Chriſts Kingdome comes not in, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 20. and thus he
accounts of all the ordinances and inſtitutions, preſcribed by Chriſt
himſelfe, in the Apoſtolical Churches, and accounts all the ſtrict
obſerving of outward formes of worſhip, is but immitating the
Saints practices, in their Babiloniſh and heatheniſh wiſedome,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117904:6"/>
all theſe outward forms, is the outward Court without the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
Pa. 1. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The lye will be found in thy owne mouth, in calling
that a lying paper, a true prophecy it is of the mighty day of the
Lord, and for thy ſaying, <hi>William Deuſberry</hi> makes it his worke
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before written thy charge is falſe, and the truth is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
againſt vain man, who in his dark minde ſeeks the Kingdome
of God in obſervations where it comes not <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 20. neither
ſhall men ſay loe here or loe there, he called by name as before
written doth witneſſe they are not the Ordinances of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
as is declared of them, they will be found and made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
to the ſhame and confuſion of their face, who in their owne
wiſedome immitates the Saints practices in forme, which they did
practice in life and power in the diſpenſation of time they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
their generation, in the manifeſtation of the ſpirit, according
to the will of God.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayſt in the 4 Pa. it is more clear, that he
prophanely compares the holy ordinances and inſtitutions of the
Lord to that great Image ſet up by <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> proud na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
ſpoken of by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and that that Image was but a tipe and
figure of this which now ſhines gloriouſly in forms and obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And thou ſayſt, that in his ſpeaking to the Anabaptiſts and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,
he tells them they have ſet up a finer Image in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
ordinances (as they call them) and what other ordinances
(thou ſayſt) doth theſe or you ſet up, but what vvas practiſed
in the Apoſtolical Churches, thus you may ſee hovv this Impoſtor,
doth reproach the holy things of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Bluſh for ſhame vvho ſayſt <hi>William Dewſberry</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares
the holy ordinances and inſtitutions of our Lord to that
great Image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Holy Ordinances, and Inſtitutions of the
Lord is not there expreſt by him, where thou ſayſt he them ſo
compares; he vvitneſſes againſt the Image you have ſet up in
your minds, of the truth as you conceive vvhere you are in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
that doth you divide into forms and obſervations as before
written to looke for the Kingdome of God to come, and though
you call them the Ordinances of Chriſt you denying Chriſt the
light you to guide in the daily croſſe, you are in the ſame nature,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117904:7"/>
wherein <hi>Nebuchadnazzar</hi> caſt the Lords ſervants into the fiery
furnace, becauſe they witneſſed againſt his Image ſo do you who
walke in your imaginations and deny Chriſt the light, cauſe the
ſervants of the Lord that walks in the life, and cannot bow to
your Image but witneſſe againſt it, to be haled out of your meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
places, beaten, ſtoned, whipt, ſtockt, impriſoned, which are
the fruits of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> nature as is manifeſt this day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
thoſe, againſt whom he witneſſeth and who is the Impoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or
and reproaches the holy things of God, the fruit makes mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
he that hath an eye to ſee let him ſee.</p>
            <p>And further thou ſayſt that he in the height of his inſolent
raſhneſſe and madneſſe, ſaith thus the word of the Lord came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
me ſaying, I will gather my people out of all forms and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,
and out of all Kindreds, Tongues and Nations, and I will
power out my ſpirit upon them. And this thou ſayſt he writes
in a different Character, as if it were all Scripture, by this you
may ſee it proved what I have accuſed them with, in denying the
Ordinances, and Adminiſtrations of the Goſpel Churches true,
and yet this impudent lyar tells me its a lying ſlander they would
render me a lyar, for telling them the truth, but it ſeems they can
rather, and with more eaſe deny the accuſation then prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
Saints, and ſtand to it, thus when they are pincht they will
ſay and un ſay, and any thing to evade.</p>
            <p>Raſhneſſe and madneſſe is thy owne, in ſpeaking evill of that
thou knoweſt not, the day will declare, the Lord will gather his
people together according as is declared, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9. And the lye
and falſe accuſation will ſtill reſt on thee, for charging <hi>W. D.</hi> as
before written, and the impudent lyar he will not be found, when
the Lord will ſeperate between the precious and the vile then
ſhall it be known, who walke in outward forms and deny Chriſt
the light and thoſe that live in the light, life and power of Chriſt,
them to lead in the daily croſſe, which keeps them in a pure life,
and holy converſation, and thy falſe accuſations doth not
us pinch, neither doe we any thing to evade, but witneſſe
the truth, againſt thy falſe accuſations, and in patience
doe finiſh our teſtimony in ſufferings, and all with us that in the
light walk, are in the ordinances of the Goſpel Church and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
the everlaſting Goſpel where all types ſhadows and figures
are done away, which thou ſo much cryes up and the Lord will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117904:7"/>
throw thee and all downe and a day of tribulation ſhall come
upon thee, and thou ſhalt not eſcape except thou repent.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou reviles us for ſaying that the ſpirit is the
only rule of faith and life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 13. which thou ſayſt that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
was made directly to the twelve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Who art thou that limits the holy one, the promiſe of
his ſpirit is to all who waite on him in the manifeſtation of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
according to the Teſtimony of Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7, 8, 9.
the manifeſtation of his Spirit is given to every one to profit
withall, for to one is given by the ſpirit the word of wiſedom to
another the word of knowledge by the ſame ſpirit, to another
faith by the ſame ſpirit, to another the gifts of healing, by the
ſame ſpirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for thy unſavory words which in reproach calls us proud
worms that vilifie and diminiſh from the Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Pride is thy owne, we doe not vilifie nor diminiſh the
Scriptures, we witneſſe them a true teſtimony of Chriſt the life,
and who in his light walk knowes the truth of the Scriptures
as it is in Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 20, 21.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayſt in confeſſion to what was declared to
thee that <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> had ſaith before the Scriptures
was written, to which thou quotes <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 1. God who at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
times, and in divers manners ſpake in times p aſt unto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken to us by his
ſon, and thou ſayſt before there was any thing commit to writeing
the Lord did more viſibly reveale his will by voice, viſion, Angels,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſince he hath committed his whole will unto writeing
by the Prophets and Apoſtles, theſe former manners are ceaſed,
and thou ſayſt to look for the ſame diſcoveries, ſtill by voice, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
or inſpiration, is madneſſe we run into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thou vain man, who dare to ſay the Lord hath ceaſed
makeing himſelfe known to his people, by voice viſion or inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
holy men of God did ſpeak, and doth ſpeak, as inſpired by
the ſpirit of God, and mooved by the Holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21.
An<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord hath promiſed in the latter daies <hi>I will power out
my ſpirit upon all fleſh, Joel. 2. 28, 29. Acts 2. 17, 18. Jer.</hi> 31.
33, 34. <hi>Heb. 8. 9, 10, 11. Iſa.</hi> 54. 13.</p>
            <p>All the Children of the Lord, who are led by his ſpirit, doth
witneſſe theſe Scriptures fulfilled and knoweth the Lord is fatith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117904:8"/>
according to his promiſe, who will recompence into thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
thy juſt reward, for ſpeaking evill of his truth, and whiles
thou denys the manifeſtation of his ſpirit, which the Lord mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts
to his people as is recorded in the Scripture of truth, thy pride
and confuſion thou haſt made manifeſt, and neither knows <hi>Moſes</hi>
miniſtry nor the Apoſtles, which thou in a buiſy minde ſpeaks of,
in thy dark underſtanding, which leads thee to fill thy Book
with falſe accuſations, as in thy 10th Pa; where thou ſayſt we
doe not make any clear difference, between the outward declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and the word of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> For the Simples ſake as we have declared the truth, we
doe declare it, which is witneſſed with all the Children of
light, the word of faith is in the heart and in the mouth, and who
are guided by it their hearts are kept pure, faith purifyes the heart
<hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9. whether they have the outward declaration yea, or
nay, and they that have the outward declaration, and though
they read it, if they minde not the word which is life and light,
which gave forth the Scripture, they do not live according to the
Scripture, for they are without faith, who are not guided by the
word, faith comes not by reading, the outward declaration, faith
is the gift of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 8 given to his Children, who diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
hearken to his word, which is life, and the life is the light of
men.</p>
            <p>And for thy chargeing us with contradictions, confuſed non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
bitter cenſures and ſhuffles, and how notorious falſe it is
wherein we ſay, that not any doth know the Scriptures by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
declaration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> To the light of Chriſt in all Conſciences we appeale, let
the righteous judge, a naturall man knows not the things that
are of God (though he read the outward declaration) for they
are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. and none is found worthy
to open the ſeales of the Book, but the Lyon of the Tribe of
<hi>Juda, &amp;c. Rev.</hi> 5. 3. 5. and then thou denys Gods ſpeaking to
his people, by voice viſion or inſpiration, and ſayeſt they run into
madneſſe that expect any ſuch thing, here thou art found in the
Contradictions confuſed nonſence, bitter cenſures and ſhuffles, and
notorious falſhoods, which thou haſt falſely charged us withall,
and its turned upon thy owne head, and proved out of thy owne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117904:8"/>
mouth, that while thou art makeing a ſhew in words to maintain
the Scripture authority, thou denyes both the diſpenſation of the
ſpirit of God in Chriſt, the light, and the Scriptures which beare
teſtimony of him, as is manifeſt in the reply to what thou haſt
writ in the 6. and 8. Pa.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou in the 11 Pa. calls us deceivers and ſaith to
thoſe thou calls thy friends, we have them abuſed by the deceite
and cheats of our owne hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Deceite and cheats thou art proved to be in, and what
thou endeavors to doe in the deceit of thy heart againſt the truth,
thou wilt ſee thy hope faile thee, and not a bleſſing but a curſe
upon thy endeavors; which to thy face is proved, in what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
written to be contrary to the diſpenſation of the ſpirit, and
Scripture, for which the terror of the Lord ſhall take hold on thee,
for thy uttering words without knowledge, and ſpeaking evill of
the things thou knoweſt not, as in the 12. Pa.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou appeals to them thou calls thy friends how
their hearts have been heated, and warmed by the power of the
word and Sacraments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which is now in contempt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,
by thoſe that ſeduce you: Which thou charges upon
us, and ſayeſt thou haſt clearly diſcovered our ſlanders, ſhifts, and
ſhuffles, and our reproaching the Ordinances, and Inſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tutions
of our Lord as Heatheniſh by compareing them to that great
Image of that heathen King, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 3. and how we deny the
Scripture to be a perfect rule of knowing God beleeving in him,
and liveing unto him, and reproach thee to be a lying ſlander for
chargeing us with that which is an apparent truth, as thou ſayſt
thou haſt proved by our lying papers, and that we have reproacht
they falſely, and the lyes are returned upon our owne heads,
whileſt thou ſayſt we witneſſe our ſelves perfect and without ſin,
and have entred the new Jeruſalem into which none ſhall enter
that makes a lye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Them thou calls thy friends, who are in the light, with
all the Children of light, doe witneſſe, that their hearts were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
warmed in Sacraments, no ſuch words is found in Scripture,
and thou that art pleading for the authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
is with the light of Chriſt in all his Saints denyed and thy
Sacraments, which is not found in Scripture, and in the light thou
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117904:9"/>
art clearly ſeen the ſlanders ſhifts and ſhuffles is thy owne, as is
manifeſt in the anſwer to the ſame reproach and accuſations, in
the 2. and 3. Page of thy Book and what we witneſſe is according
to Scripture, which we owne, and in many things thou haſt writ,
as before is manifeſt by thy owne words, the Scripture thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes,
ſo on whoſe head the falſhood remains, to the Children of
light is made manifeſt and the day will further declare it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
Chriſt our King ſhall be exalted over all, in whom our perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and cleanſing from ſin is, and lead us into new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> into
which nothing enters that works abomination or makes a lye,
but who enter therein are led by the ſpirit of Chriſt in whoſe
mouth is found no guile, he that hath an ear to heare let him
heare.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayſt to ſome of them thou calls thy friends,
ſome of you have heard <hi>W. Dewſberry</hi> ſay of himſelf, that he,
was as perfect as that Chriſt hat died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> this is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
by one of credit and fidelity amongſt your ſelves. I forbear his
name. In <hi>Deweſberry</hi> new birth he thus witneſſeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy ſpirit in the light is ſeen, who hath publiſhed what
thou hath received from a nameleſſe Author, and thy acuſation
is falſe, which thou haſt publiſhed to the world, there were never
any heard <hi>W. Deweſberry</hi> ſay of himſelf that he was as perfect as
that Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that thou calls his new
birth will be a witneſſe againſt thee, There is no ſuch word ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt
by him, as thou ſayeſt this nameleſſe Author hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
of him. In the preſence of God He (called <hi>W. Deweſber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.)</hi>
doth witneſſe that ſelf is imperfect, and ſelfe righteouſneſſe
as a filthy ragg and a menſtruous cloth, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa. 64. 6. And he
doth witneſſe Chriſt Jeſus the true light which lighteth everyone
that comes into the world, Joh.</hi> 1. 9. which diſcovers the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
and filthyneſſe of ſelf, with all its righteouſneſſe, and his
perfection is in Chriſt, the light, which he doth witneſſe, the
ſame Chriſt and no other, but he which ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
who is the brightneſſe of his fathers glory, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 1. 3. 13.
8. which he thou falſely accuſes, as before written, which all the
Children of light doth witneſſe, the Righteouſneſſe of God in
Chriſt the light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. which for the Simples ſake the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117904:9"/>
truth is witneſſed forth in the preſence of God, which the Lord
will clear, from the lyes and ſlanders caſt upon it, and he ſhall
be known what he is, whom you call a proud polluted worme,
that dare exalt himſelf to a perfection equall with God, which
are thy owne words and what thou haſt gathered up from other
who falſely accuſe as thou doſt, which words were not ſpoken by
him, thou cals a proud polluted worme, who can bear thy revile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
but for the truths ſake, that the Simple do not ſtumble, at
the way of truth, doth witneſſe againſt thy falſe accuſations and
revileings, which thou haſt filled thy Book withall.</p>
            <p>As in the 14. and 15. Pa, Speaking to them thou calls friends
whom thou ſayſt is ſeduced, and thou declares that thoſe whom
thou charges with ſeducing them doth teach them to ceaſe from
all religious duties of commanded worſhip, without ſcruple or
checke of Conſcience, before they can enjoy God, or be taught
immediately what to do, firſt put out the true light, and power
of Conſcience to do his office, by de ſpiſing the means of enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and convincing it to act in the ſoul, and then reſolves to
follow the immediate commands of Conſcience, without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning
the Author of thoſe Lawes at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy accuſation is falſ, we do not teach any to ceaſe from
all religious duties of commanded worſhip, neither put out the
true light, we teach all to be obedient to the commands of God,
who ſaith this is my beloved Son in whom I am wel-pleaſed, hear
him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 5. And we bear teſtimony of him that he is the
true light that lighteth every one that comes into the world,
<hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 9. and convinces the world of ſin, Righteouſneſſe and
Judgement, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 8. and he alone commands in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
for God, and is the Author of the perfect Law, handed in the
hand of a mediator, to whom we exhort all to be ſubject, and in
whom all the Children of light walk, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
            <p>And for thy expreſſing, a depth of deceit and deluſion, which
thou charges upon us, which is found in thy ſelf who hath made
lyes thy refuge to ſlander the innocent which is further manifeſt
in thy 16. Pa.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayſt we take no notice of Scripture authority, as if they
were altogether out of date, which falſe accuſation is witneſſed
againſt in what is returned in anſwer to the preface of thy
Book.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117904:10"/>
And in the 17. and 18. Pa. thou charges us with impudent fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads
to make a ſhew of one thing, and intend another, purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
minded to deceive, and yet they tell us often that as they
write ſo they meane, and ſpeak the truth in plaineſſe, moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
hypocriſy and deceit, which nothing but a lying and a kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh
head, dare goe about to excuſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all thoſe unſavory words as before written, wherein thou
ſayſt we have diſcovered to purpoſe the deceit of our anſwer, in
ſaying the revelations of Chriſt are according to Scripture, and
where the new Covenant is witneſt, the law is written in the
heart, and the witneſſe and teſtimony of Jeſus within bearing
witneſſe with our ſpirits, that we are the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Doing any thing of purpoſe to deceive, through hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſye
or knaviſh heads, we deny, and in the preſence of God
we ſpeak the truth in plaineſſe, and doe witneſſe there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit
in ſaying the revelations of Chriſt are according to Scripture
and all in the new Covenant do know, the law of God written
in their hearts, and the witneſſe or teſtimony of Jeſus, within, 1
<hi>Jo.</hi> 5. 10. bearing witneſſe with their ſpirits that they are the
Children of God. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8. 16. and this declared is neither deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
nor knaviſh, which is the unſavory words thou charges on us,
let the truth of God in all Conſciences judge, to whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long,
the Scriptures we are not againſt, they bear teſtimony of
Chriſt the light whom we witneſſe the way to the father. <hi>Mat.</hi>
1. 27. <hi>None knows the father but the Son, and he to whom the
Son will reveale him,</hi> by the revelation of the Spirit of God, is
the things of God knowne to his people, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9. 10. 13.
<hi>Ro.</hi> 8. 11. 16. according as is recorded we witneſſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
fulfilled in Chriſt the light who is our life, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 3. 4.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou queries, did ever any read of the law and
teſtimony in the heart, and that the law and teſtimony in the
heart, is the law of the new Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Who hath read the Scripture in the fear of God, hath
read what the Lord hath promiſed as declared, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 16. Bind
up the teſtimony, ſeal the law, among my Diſciples, and <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.
33. <hi>This ſhall be the Covenant. I will make with the houſe of Iſrael,
in thoſe daies ſaith the Lord, I will put my Lawes in their inward
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117904:10"/>
parts, and write it in their hearts, Heb.</hi> 8. 10 11, 12. and the
law written in the heart we witneſſe, and the Lord faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
in performing according to his Promiſe in the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>And thou goes on in the 19. and 20. Pa, calling us impoſtors
and pervertors of the new Covenant, and to be in Idle proud
fancyes, and itching humors of our owne brains in our Apoſtate
Condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> We in the light can bear thy reproach, and have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed
the truth that it may ſtand a witneſſe againſt thy revileings,
and in the Lord we reſt, who will make manifeſt, whether thou or
we be the perverters of the new Covenant, and guilty of what
thou charges us with.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou in the 22. Pa. ſayes that <hi>W. Deweſberry.</hi>
tells us that the mighty day of the Lord is appeared in the
North of England, and is riſeing towards the South, and ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſpread
this Nation, and all the Natious of the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
what the mans fancy and deſigne is in bruiting and makeing ſuch
a noiſe of the appearance of the mighty day of the Lord judge ye,
I am ſure he hath ſufficiently diſcovered his owne folly in blazing
abroad ſuch dreams of his owne lying heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> In thy 2. Pa. thou hath enlarged thy ſelf concerning
that Book calling it a lying paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the truth is witneſſed
in anſwer to thy charge, and this in anſwer to what is here writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
fancies, bruitiſhneſſe, folly dreams, and lyes, <hi>W. Deuſberry</hi>
denys the truth he hath declared, as the Lord hath him moved,
in faithfullneſſe to the ſouls of all people, that they be not found
the ſloathfull ſervants, putting the day of the Lord a farr off, in
this his day wherein the houre of his righteous judgement is
come, <hi>(Rev.</hi> 14. 7.) to all that wait on him, the truth is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
that all men may prepare in the light the Lord to meet, and
no longer in ſloathfulneſſe remain, leaſt he come upon them as a
theife in the night, and if the day of the Lord do not ariſe over
all the world, and the kingdoms of the world, become the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
of our Lord and his Chriſt, and the Lord, performe not as
is declared, then ſay the Lord harh not ſpoken by me who is
known to the world by name <hi>William Dewſberry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 22. Pa. thou ſays we have ſet our ſelves in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117904:11"/>
Throne of Chriſt judging the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy accuſation is falſe, ſelf we deny, to Chriſt we are
ſnbject who ſits on his Throne, and is come and comeing in his
Saints to judge the world, <hi>Jude 14, 15. 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 2. and 2.
5.</p>
            <p>And in the 23. Pa. thou ſayſt, why do not we command the
dead to riſe, and appear before us, and many other unſavory
words are there expreſt.</p>
            <p>Reply. A wicked and adultrous generation, ſhall ſeek after a
ſigne, and there ſhall no ſigne be given it, but the ſigne of the Prophet
Jona, Mat. 16. 4.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou charges <hi>Howgill,</hi> and <hi>Burrough</hi> (as thou
calls them) with pernitious blaſphemous opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy accuſation is falſe, they are faithfull men, ſerveing
their generation in the light, Miniſters of Chriſt, in whom is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed
the God head dwelling bodily, <hi>Coll.</hi> 2. 9. and in him
were one in God, they that joyne to the Lord are one ſpirit, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17. he that can receive it let him.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou in the 29. Pa. ſaith that the Revelations of
Chriſt that are according to Scripture, are either texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
expreſſed, or rationall deductions conſequences and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;
that naturally flow from particular paſſages of Scriptures,
and not any other revelations can be pleaded for as rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thy dark minde is ſhut out from knowing the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of Chriſt, and though thou ſay that anſwer that was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
to theſe words was not to purpoſe, it ſtands a witneſſe againſt
thee, and will be found to purpoſe in the light, when thy reward
thou ſhalt have, for all thy unſavory words expreſt in thy
Book.</p>
            <p>And in the 33. Pa. where thou falſely accuſes us, that we will
allow of no Laws of God nor Scripture, but the Revelations and
edicts of our owne bewitched hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when thou haſt
reviled us with falſe accuſation as before written, thou beſeeches
thoſe thou call, thy dear friends to be ſerious in their thoughts of
what thou haſt written, in diſcovering our deceits and blaſphemies
denying the rule that all things are to be tryed by, and make
themſelves the abſolute rule, and we muſt not queſtion what they
ſay though it be never ſo inſolent, and to be abhorred of all ſober
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117904:11"/>
Chriſtians <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Thou hath brazned thy face to ſlander the truth of
God, with lyes and blaſphemies, which is the foundation of all
hereſy, and there thou art found and thy accuſation is falſe,
Chriſt the rule that all things is to be tryed by, we owne and
our ſelves deny, and to the light of Chriſt in all Conſciences, we
appeale, whether thou or we deny the rule, thou that ſayſt the
revelations of Chriſt, are either texts of Scripture expreſſed, or
rationall deductions conſequences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before written, or we
who witneſſe Chriſt the true light, revealed by the father, <hi>and
none knows the father but the Son and he to whom the Son will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale
him, Mat. 11. 27. Luke</hi> 10. 22, Let all that are in Chriſt
with ſobriety in the light judge.</p>
            <p>And for the reſt of thy ſlanders in the 37. and 38. Pa. where
thou ſays, theſe miſerable worms uncovenant themſelves and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Chriſt
themſelves, as if they cared not for grace and mercy in ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
before God, denying the Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in the 40. Pa.
thou ſayſt of thoſe in ſcorne called Quakers, thou can ſafely ſay
they deny the benefit that comes to the Church, by Chriſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in that fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he received from the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or elſe
deny it to be are all body of fleſh and ſo make it but a tipe and a
figure of Chriſt in the Saints who are his true real body, which he
now ſuffers in, and by his ſuffering makes ſatisfaction, for them
makeing the death of the Croſſe of none effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The miſerable worms that uncovenant themſelves and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Chriſt,
themſelves, who denys Chriſt the light thou art found to
be one, whom thy dark minde art working abomination, and
makeing lies, which thou haſt publiſhed to the world, in thy
Books, and thy place thou may read as is recorded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 27.
and the reſt of thy accuſations, recorded in 40. Pa. we witneſſe
againſt, and for the Simple ſake declare as followeth that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
came to the Church by Chriſt ſuffering, in that body God
gave which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and with one offering
hath Chriſt perfected for ever, them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.
14. and theſe are his Saints in whom he is now revealed, who are
his body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 23. which now ſuffered by thee, and all that are
of the murdering generation, who bore falſe witneſſe againſt
Chriſt, when he was in that body which they crucified at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117904:12"/>
and thou haſt manifeſt thy ſelf to be of the ſame murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
generation, who hath publiſhed to the world the falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
againſt the innocent, to perfect thy evill intent, towards
the body of Chriſt, if the Lord prevent thee not, but thou ſhalt
know the Lord faithfull, that thou and all that formes your
tongues againſt him ſhall fall in judgement, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. 17.</p>
            <p>And what is charged upon thee in anſwer to thy reply to the
anſwer to the third queſtion, that thou ſets at nought the corner
ſtone, and prefers the teſtimony of him before him, limitting the
eternall ſon of God as thou hath in what is Printed in the 55. Pa.
where thou ſpeaks of the Scripture that they are deſigned of
God, to be the only inſtrument and veſſel of his ſpirit, to convey
the knowledge of Chriſt as Redeemer to loſt man, and without
them Chriſt is not knowne at all to any ſaveing ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Who art thou that dare thus utter words without
knowledge, Chriſt is knowne where the Father reveales him to be
the ſouls life, whether they have the Scripture yea, or nay, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the will of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he makes knowne his minde of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
who wait upon him in his feare, and the ſecrets of the Lord are
with thoſe that fear him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 14. And the ſpirit of the
Lord is witneſſe with our ſpirits that we are the children of God,
O man repent, leaſt the Lord cut thee off, and thou periſh in thy
gainſayings.</p>
            <p>And further what thou hath written in Reply, to what was
returned in anſwer to the queſtion before mentioned, the moſt
of the falſe accuſations is anſwered, in what was returned to the
former part of the Book and all thy falſe accuſations and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
denyed with the light, and for the Simples ſake there is retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in anſwer to thy queſtions which thou haſt propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Qu.</hi> Where we read of a perfect law of God in the heart,
and where it is made the Rule and Ground of the Saints obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Law of God is perfect, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. and is the rule
to which the Saints are to walke in obedience to, and to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 12. and the Law to be in the heart is proved,
<hi>Pſal. 40. 8. I delight to do thy will O God, yea thy law is within
my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117904:12"/>
2. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the law in the heart be under another Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
diſtinct from, the perfect law of God declared in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Qu.</hi> What were to underſtand by the law of God i n the
heart, which is the ſame with Scripture, whether the 10. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
written in Tables of ſtone onely, or all thoſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Precepts of Goſpel worſhip and obedience conjoyned with
them alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To thy 2. and 3. Queſtion in the old Covenant the
Law was written in Tables of ſtone, which Law haveing a ſhadow
of good things to come and not the very image of the things,
can never with thoſe ſacrifices which they offered year by year
continually make the comers thereunto perfect. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 1. And
when he came who ſaith, Lo I come to do thy will O God, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
away the firſt that he may eſtabliſh the ſecond, ver. 9. by
which will we are ſanctified thorow the offering of the body of
Jeſus Chriſt once for all, ver. 10. and by one offering he hath
perfected for ever them, that are ſanctified, whereof the holy
Ghoſt is a witneſſe to us, as he ſaid before, <hi>this is the covenant that
I will make with them, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Lawes in
their hearts, and in their minds will I write them, ver.</hi> 14, 15, 16.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 33.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the Law in the heart, without the uſe of
Scriptures make any Evangelical diſcoveries of the perſon, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
and Offices of Chriſt, as he is Redeemer of loſt man?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thy feigned words we wave, the truth we witneſſe,
the Law in the heart witneſſed in the New Covenant, Chriſt is
known to be King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 15.
And the faithfull High Prieſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 17. 3. 1. 4. 15. 5. 6 7.
26. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. who hath made us Kings and Prieſts to God and
his Father, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether all ſhall be ſaved, that have the Law of God
written in their hearts, by virtue of the New Covenant, or any
be ſaved that live to years of diſcretion, that know not Chriſt,
as the Scriptures teſtifie of him, in order to his coming to the
world to ſave ſinners?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All are ſaved, who are guided by the righteous Law of
the Spirit of life in Chriſt, which ſets them free from the Law of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117904:13"/>
ſin and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 2. And what years ſoever any live unto,
they have no diſcretion to know Chriſt, as the Scriptures teſtifie
of him, but they who in his light waits upon him, to be guided
by him; for who hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, is none of his,
<hi>Rom,</hi> 8. 9.</p>
            <p>And for the reſt of thy aſperſions, and revilings thou haſt
writ, calling us deceivers that fear the Authority of man, or elſe
we would deny Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Chriſt we do not deny, but him we own, who reſpects
no mans perſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 11. and in him no fear of man is, and
we in him Reigns over thee, and all the authority of the power
of darkneſſe, that ſtands in oppoſition to Chriſt, the Son of God,
to whom every knee muſt bow, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10. the day ſhall declare
it.</p>
            <p>And in what thou haſt replied, to the Anſwer to the fourth
Queſtion, which thou charges to be untrue, to ſay <hi>That man in
the fall, as he ſtands in the ſtate of corrupt nature, hath not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
any light without Chriſt, to doe any thing acceptable to God,</hi> &amp;c.
Which thou goes about to prove the contrary, and ſaith there is
the light and uſe of reaſon, and underſtanding faculties, though
corrupted.</p>
            <p>And further thou ſayes, This light of corrupt reaſon, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
expreſt, preſents to the conſcience good and evill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> In the light thou art ſeen to be in the corrupt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
from whence all theſe corrupt words hath come, which thou
haſt Printed in thy Book, and thy words are not true. Corrupt
reaſon of man doth not preſent to the conſcience, things good
and evill, a corrupt Tree cannot bring forth good fruit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7,
18. There is nothing makes manifeſt darkneſſe, but light, <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
5. 15. which all men in the Fall is gone from, out of the way,
and there is none that doth good, no not one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 9, 10,
11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the naturall man receives not the things that are
of God, nor can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 14. And all the righteouſneſſe of man in
this ſtate, is as a filthy rag, and a menſtruous cloath, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64. 6.
And this is the ſtate of man in corrupt nature: And the light
that convinces man of this dark and corrupt eſtate he is in, is
the light of Chriſt that convinces the World of ſin, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117904:13"/>
and judgement, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8. So we that were ſometimes
darkneſſe, are now light in the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 8. And who
walk in the light, there is no occaſion of ſtumbling, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.
10.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayeſt, Thou knowes we will lye, as thou
haſt made it manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is not ſo, thou hath not made yet manifeſt any lye
that we have ſpoken, by any truth thou hath declared.</p>
            <p>And thou goes on, as in thy 89 Page thou ſayes, The rational
ſoul of man corrupted, is called the candle of the Lord, which we
invent to be Chriſt; which is falſe, we deny that the corrupt
ſoul of man is the candle of the Lord, or Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And further thou ſayes, It was thy intended work to goe
thorow all the Anſwers to the ten Queſtions, but for want of
thy paper, which thou ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es we detained from thee, contrary to
our Promiſe.</p>
            <p>In which thou ſays not true, for the promiſe was to thee thou
ſhould have a coppy of thy paper which thou ſent to us when it
was ready for thee, which was not then written, neither was any
time ſet down of thy haveing it, and as way was made, a coppy
according to our promiſe, came to thy hands.</p>
            <p>And in the cloſe of thy Book, thou goes on as thou begun,
ſaying we deny Scriptures as to the end they were intended, and
reproach the Ordinances of the Lord Jeſus, which the Scriptures
teach, under the notion of heatheniſh worſhips, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is
anſwered to in the truth declared, a witneſſe to ſtand againſt all
the reproaches, that thou haſt caſt upon the truth of the liveing
God, and the God thou art pleading for cannot crown thee with
honour, in the day wherein the liveing God will exalt his ſon,
and clear the innocency of his people, then ſhall the God whoſe
worſhip thou art defending, be confounded, and confuſion
and ſhame ſhall ſtop thy mouth, and if this come not to paſſe as
declared, then ſay the Lord hath not ſpoken by me.</p>
            <p>And in that thou calls thy Poſt-ſcript in the end of thy Book,
the things therein thou falſely accuſes us with, and calls them the
Rocks which we are to manifeſt how we ſhall eſcape, which is
clearly made manifeſt in what is written in anſwer to thy Book.
Only this, where thou ſayes we make no difference between the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117904:14"/>
viſible profeſſing Church, and the Pagan world, all may be ſaved
alike if they will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> They that make a viſible Profeſſion of Chriſt, and
deny to walk in the light of his Spirit, are of the world that lies
in wickedneſſe, 1 <hi>John 5. 19. Mat.</hi> 7. 21. as well as them thou
calls the Pagan world; and not any can be ſaved by what they
doe in their own wills, all that is done in that nature is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to God, as is plain in the Anſwer to what thou haſt writ in
the 70 Page. <hi>It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth,
but of God that ſhewes mercy,</hi> Rom. 9. 16. which he makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
in the riches of his grace, in Chriſt the light, who leads all
that obey him, in the ſtrait way of ſelf-deniall, and the daily
croſſe, in obedience to the will of God, which is our ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<hi>And he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are one,
Heb. 2. 4. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 31. He that can receive it, let him.</p>
            <p>For the truths ſake, that the ſimple be not turned out of the
way, by the falſe accuſations, reproaches, and aſperſions thou haſt
caſt upon it, what is before written in Anſwer to thee, the truth
doth clear, and the Anſwer to thy ten Queſtions, which thou
charges to be deceitfull, that they may witneſſe for themſelves
againſt what thou haſt caſt upon them, that all that deſire to
know the truth may them read. The Queſtions and Anſwers
are as followeth.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the writings of the Scriptures are a declaration
of the Holy will and mind of God, that neceſſarily oblige the ſervants
of God that profeſſe them, to believe and obſerve whatever is revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
therein, to be believed and done; and whether the Scripture
alone be a perfect Rule of faith and life, unto all of years amongſt
us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea or nay?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures is a true declaration of the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
amongſt the Saints, and a true teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt,
but not any doth them know, neither can believe what is written
therein, by the outward declaration and teſtimony of Scripture,
but by the word of Faith, which is in the heart, and in the mouth,
which is the word of Faith which we Preach, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>2 Qu. <hi>Whether any other Revelations and Obſervations, not
to be found in the Scripture, be binding to the conſciences of thoſe</hi>
perſons that have the benefit of the Scripture, or whether ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117904:14"/>
revelations or dictates within a mans heart and ſoul, be as bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the conſcience, and to be urged to a mans ſelf, or others,
as the Scriptures are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The revelations of Jeſus Chriſt, is according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
which Revelations binds up the Teſtimony, and ſeals the
Law in the hearts of his Diſciples; and what dictates is in the
conſcience or heart of man, contrary to the Law and Teſtimony,
is not to be regarded, but diſowned and judged with the light
which comes from Chriſt, the Saints life, who guides them in
a pure life, and holy converſation, according to Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.
20.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether any thing beſides the Scripture, is conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
of the bleſſed God to reveal Chriſt as Redeemer and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
to the ſpirit of miſerable loſt man, to bring man unto hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,
or whether corrupt man without the knowledge of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
may ordinarily attain unto ſalvation, yea or nay?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No man can come to the Son any other way, but
whom the Father draweth by the power of his unlimited Spirit,
and never any ſhall know the Father, but he to whom the Son
reveals him; and he that thinks to attain the way to eternall
life, by reading the letter of the Scripture, and regards not the
light that comes from Chriſt, that witneſſeth for God in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
of the heart and conſcience, he deceives himſelf, for the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
of eternall life is ſealed up in the ſealed Book, from all the
Sons and Daughters of men; and none ſhall ever know it by the
outward teſtimony of Scripture, but by the inſpiration of the
Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> who is
found worthy to open the ſeals of the Book, and <hi>is the way, the
truth, and the life,</hi> to all that in his light wait, his power them to
guide, in faithfull obedience to the righteous and perfect Law of
God, written in the heart, for the exerciſe of the conſcience,
which keeps them void of offence towards God, and towards
men, according to teſtimony of Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 16. 23. 1.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether that light of conſcience which is more or
leſſe in all ſince the fall, be the remains or ſome reliques left of
the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in reference to the Covenant of works, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
common to all, from the redemption of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi>
as flowing from the Covenant of grace, or how elſe? I deſire
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117904:15"/>
you would clearly expreſſe your thoughts in this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Man in the fallen eſtate hath not any light remains in
him, to guide him to doe any thing well pleaſing to God, as he
ſtands in the ſtate of corrupt nature; for all his righteouſneſſe is
as filthy rags, and as a menſtruous cloth, the light that convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
man and woman of the evill of their hearts, and diſcovers
the filthineſſe of all their own righteouſneſſe, is the light that
comes from Chriſt, the true light that lighteth every man that
comes into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1. 9. And this light is not common
to man by nature, it is the great gift of God, his grace that hath
appeared, and teacheth all that are guided by it, to deny all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and worldly luſts, and to live godily and ſoberly in
this preſent evill world; and all that walk contrary to the light,
this is their condemnation, the light, <hi>John</hi> 3. 19.</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the end of God in giving and continuing
this kind of light to all men in the world, was not to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint
and curb to the exorbitant luſts of ſo corrupt a creature
as man, and ſo made ſubſervant to God in the Government of
the world, in order to the peace and continuance of the ſame, and
to leave all without excuſe, Or what beſides this the end of God
was, that this kind of light ſhould be minded and improved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the power of man by what he is from creation or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall
grace or redemption, in order to eternall happineſſe; and
the not heeding this light in all men, ſhall be the only condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of the world. Or whether this light be the Goſpel, or
Chriſt, or his Spirit, or whether it be a light either equall with,
or inferiour to, or of a different kind with the Scriptures?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The light which comes from Chriſt is given of God,
to guide the creature out of its own ſtrength and power, to
Chriſt the mighty power and wiſedome of God, the creature
to guide with moderation, in the uſe of all creatures, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
and govern the creation to the praiſe and glory of God:
And this light is of the pure nature of God, and leads to Chriſt
the everlaſting Goſpel. And this is the condemnation of the
world, that hates the light which comes from Chriſt, becauſe
they believe not in him, <hi>John</hi> 3. 18.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the light of Conſcience the light of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
the light of providence, the light of grace, ought not to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117904:15"/>
be preſt upon all, to reforme them, and draw them up to a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
pitch of Chriſtian obedience, according to the written word of
the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thou with all who are in the light is ſeen to be in thy
wiſedome, querying after many lights, but as is formerly written,
in anſwer to thy 4. <hi>Queſt.</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is but one true light, Chriſt who
lighteth every one that comes into the world, and all his miniſters
turnes the mindes of people from darkneſſe to Chriſt the true
light, in it to waite on him for his power to deſtroy the power
of Satan, and to lead in the ſtraite narrow way of ſelf denyal and
the daily Croſſe, which is the way into the Kingdome of God,
<hi>who ever will be my Diſciple,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he muſt deny himſelf,
and take up his Croſſe daily, and follow me, Luke</hi> 19. 23.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether a ſinner condemned by the Law, is made
juſt before God, unto eternall life, by an inherent power within,
or worke of Sanctification, or whether by the ſatisfaction, and
ſuffering of Chriſt in mans nature, and behalfe,, reſted on by
faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Creature whoſe Conſcience is awakened by the
light, the righteous Law of God in the heart, which ſhews it, its
ſinfull ſtate, and ſtands condemned before the Throne of God for
diſobeying the light, ſhall never be juſtified by any ſelf righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
for it is uncleanneſſe in the ſight of God, for juſtification
is through faith in the Lord Jeſus, but this faith which layes hold
on Chriſt for juſtification, is not attained by any power the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
hath of its ſelf, neither can any know it, who receive honor
one of another, <hi>Joh. 5. 44. How can ye beleeve who receive honor
one of another, and ſeek not the honor that comes from God onely,</hi>
faith is the gift of God, given to the Children of light, who waits
in the light on the Lord, in the way of his judgements, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 8.
till judgement be brought forth into victory, that the creature be
brought into true poverty, of ſpirit, for ever to periſh, without
free redemption in the Lord Jeſus, which the father in his appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
time, reveales the ſon to the ſoule, that ſtands condemned
before him, and by the arme of his mighty power, creates it to a
lively hope, and he that hath this hope in him purifieth himſelf,
even as he is pure, ſo whom he juſtifieth he ſanctifieth, and he
that ſaith he is juſtified and liveth in ſin deceiveth himſelf, for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117904:16"/>
faith purifieth the heart, and purgeth the Conſcience from
dead works to ſerve the liveing God, which is witneſſed in the
Children of light, according to teſtimony of Scripture. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.
14.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the perſon or eſſence of Chriſt, or his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
dwell in any upon earth, or whether by his gifts and graces
onely, or whether all thoſe that have Chriſt in them, muſt forſake
all outward teaching of men, and whether the Scripture be but a
dead letter, and of no uſe, otherwaies then Chriſt within doth
witneſſe unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that knows not Chriſt to be in him is a reprobate,
for he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is none of his, and he
that is guided by the ſpirit of Chriſt, needs not any teaching of
man, <hi>(for you ſhall not neede to teach one another, for all my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
ſhall be taught of me, ſaith the Lord God,)</hi> and the Scripture
is but a killing letter, but of uſe in its place,d teſtimony of Chriſt,
but not any knows Chriſt by it, for Chriſt is known by the light
of his ſpirit, which gave forth the Scriptures, and all that are gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by his ſpirit knows the Scripture in the truth as it is in Jeſus,
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph.</hi> 4. 21.</p>
            <p>9. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the converſion that was wrought upon
the ſouls of many, under the ordinary outward miniſtry of the
word, in our publique aſſembles, turning men from darkneſſe to
light, from prophaneſſe to true Godlineſſe, be true unto ſalvation,
and whether thoſe that have been thus converted were in the
ſtate of ſalvation, before they joyned themſelves unto your ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,
or whether can none be converted, and ſaved, that never
came under, nor gave their aſſent to the diſpenſation of your
way, and how you will juſtifye yours to be in the true and good
old way, that all have and ſhall be ſaved in, you may do well to
make it out by ſome evident demonſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Who can witneſſe a true converſion by the power of
the ſpirit of God, in turning their mindes from darkneſſe to light,
that comes from Chriſt, and in his light waite to receive the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
of death in themſelves, to deſtroy all ſelf confidence in any
thing below Chriſt, and in the ſtate of death to wait till that they
heare the voice of the Son of God, and by his power was raiſed
up to a liveing hope in Chriſt to walk, who throw his blood do
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117904:16"/>
witneſſe their garments waſhed and made white, to reigne Kings
and Preiſts upon the earth for ever, to worſhip the father in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
and truth, and who ever can witneſſe this converſion whether
it were wrought when they frequented your publique aſſemblies,
or abſented from them, this converſion we owne who it can
witneſſe, and of our way they are, and will to us come, and all
ſhall know the truth we witneſſe is the good old way, that all
ſouls that came to God walked in, Chriſt the way the truth and
the life, the ancient of daies, which was before time, but manifeſt
in time in all the Children of light, who doth them lead in the
narrow way of ſelf denial, and the daily Croſs, with him to enter,
thorow the ſtrait gate, into the holy City, new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where
the ſoule hath union which the father of light, and beholds his
face, and his name is written in their foreheads, and there is no
night there, neither need of <hi>Candle, nor light of the Sun, for the
Lord God giveth them light, and they ſhall reigne for ever and ever,
Rev.</hi> 22. 5.</p>
            <p>10. Whether any of your way attaine unto perfection in this
life, that they can truly ſay that they do all that God commands,
without failing, either in matter or in manner of obedience, no
not in thought, word and deed, and whether the perſons of any
ſtand juſt before God, that are not thus perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All that are in the way we are in, which is Chriſt the
way to the Father, in whom all in their meaſure are preſſing on
to the fulneſs of ſtature in Chriſt the perfect man, and who in him
is grown to the fulneſſe of ſtature, in his power doth ſtand, which
doth them guide, that in their mouthes is found no guile, for they
are without fault before the Throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 5.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
